Well, it's the 1930s and apparently
Americans suffering the economic ravages
of the Great Depression were in no mood
for an old deal and so my dear people
that means it's time to talk about the
New Deal. So if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it. All
right, so in case you didn't watch the
previous video on the Great Depression,
let me Heim-splain it up real quickly.
So in October of 1929 the US stock
market crashed real hard and that
plunged the United States into a severe
economic depression and not just your
garden variety average depression. No,
this was a Great Depression. And to many
Americans this turn of events wasn't
altogether unexpected slap in the face
because the 1920s was a decade marked by
enormous economic growth and prosperity.
But much of that growth was fueled by
deregulation of businesses and the
expansion of buying consumer goods and
stock shares on credit. And so when the
bottom fell out in 1929 many Americans
were persuaded that laissez-faire
Republican economic policies were to
blame. And they were further convinced
of this conviction as the Republican
president Herbert Hoover, who was in
office when the depression began, didn't
do much to help the country recover. And
so that far too brief context sets the
stage for the presidential election of
1932 which was a contest between two
very different ideological approaches to
solving America's economic crisis. On
one side you had the Republican
incumbent Herbert Hoover who made very
few legislative attempts to solve the
problems of the depression since he
believed deeply in government restraint
and laissez-faire policies. And then on
the other side you had the Democrat
Franklin D. Roosevelt who argued that
Americans should expect the federal
government to take decisive and bold
action in order to make their lives
better especially regarding the profound
difficulties of the depression. And as
it turned out Roosevelt won the election
by a dang landslide and he took that
victory as a mandate to get the federal
government busy trying to solve the
problems created by the depression. And
his plan for doing so was known as the
New Deal. And there were three major
categories of reform that this plan
addressed. Oh, and by the way, if you
want note guides to follow along with
this video and all my videos, check that
link in the description. But before I
tell you what those three categories
are, I need to tell you what ideology
drove Roosevelt's actions, namely
Keynesian economics. So the British
economist John Maynard Keynes argued
that government spending is the
mechanism which will increase consumer
demand and thus lift an economy out of
depression. And that is the key to this
system. The government is responsible
for spending money in order to correct
the economy and it should do so even if
it racks up budget deficits. And this of
course was a big departure from the
conservative economic policies of the
1920s. Anyway, like I said, through the
New Deal Roosevelt aimed to address what
he called the three Rs: relief,
recovery, and reform. And let's briefly
consider each one. So first, the New
Deal offered relief for the unemployed.
And my goodness, did the US have some
unemployed folks. I mean, at the end of
1929, the unemployment rate was
somewhere in the neighborhood of 3 to
4%, which is to say, for every 100
Americans, about three or four of them
were out of work. But by 1933, the
unemployment rate soared to around 25%,
which in case you're keeping score is a
real bad. And although employment had
generally been the responsibility of the
private sector, you know, like
businesses, Roosevelt swung the New Deal
at it and decided that the federal
government would put Americans to work.
And so, the New Deal created works
programs like the Public Works
Administration, which employed Americans
to do federal infrastructure work like
building roads and dams and bridges. And
similarly, you had the Tennessee Valley
Authority, which hired people to run
electric power plants, which did work to
control flooding and erosion. And then
also, you had the Civilian Conservation
Corps, which employed young men between
the ages of 18 and 24 to manage soil
conservation and forestry projects. And
as a result, by 1937, the unemployment
rate had dropped to about 15%, which you
know, like it's still bad, but you know,
improvement is improvement. Now, all
those programs that I just mentioned
were kind of more long-term cures, but
Roosevelt also deployed short-term
emergency measures to stabilize the
economy as well. For example, during his
first 100 days in office, Roosevelt
declared a bank holiday, which shut
banks down for several days until they
reopened with federal inspection and
assistance. And when banks did reopen,
they were supported by the Emergency
Banking Act, which among other things,
directed the Federal Reserve to issue
currency that would help banks keep up
with demands for cash. And all that
taken together meant that the federal
government now exercised much more
control over America's financial system
and therefore helped restore Americans'
faith in banks. Okay, and the second R
the New Deal addressed was recovery for
businesses. And a good example here is
the National Industrial Recovery Act of
1933. You see, Roosevelt believed that
one of the main factors causing economic
hardship was cutthroat competition in
the business sector that had caused
workers wages to remain low, which in
turn meant that they couldn't buy as
much. And so the NIRA sought to resolve
this problem by establishing a set of
codes agreed upon by representatives
from the laboring community and
representatives from competing
corporations. And these codes created
security for workers by establishing
minimum wage levels and shorter working
hours and regulation of prices of
certain petroleum products. And the
third area addressed by the New Deal was
reform of economic institutions. And
here I'll only mention two programs.
First, because many folks had lost
confidence in the banking system at the
outset of the depression, the
Glass-Steagall Act came in to shore up
that confidence. Essentially, it
increased regulation in banks and
limited the ways that banks could invest
people's money. And to this end, the
Glass-Steagall Act gave birth to a new
entity called the Federal Deposit
Insurance Corporation, which guaranteed
people's bank deposits with federal
money. And then the second example of
economic reform you need to know is the
Social Security Act of 1935, which
provided a safety net of income for
workers over the age of 65. Basically,
part of a worker's wages were withheld
by the federal government and then paid
back to them reached retirement age. And
that program is still going today. And
here's the thing, the scope of New Deal
programs was, to put it mildly,
expansive. And I've only given you the
briefest introduction to a small sample
of those programs. But the point to
remember is this, the New Deal
transformed the United States into a
limited welfare state, and many of those
reforms have endured to the present day.
But here's where I tell you that no
matter how well-intentioned Roosevelt
was in his voluminous attempts to New
Deal his way out of the crisis, the
Great Depression kept on depressing and
was stubbornly unresponsive to any
attempt to find a solution. meant that
over time two groups leveled criticisms
at Roosevelt and his New Deal. And so
let me introduce you to them. First of
all, conservatives criticized Roosevelt
for using too much federal power, and
they laid out their gripes in a document
known as the Conservative Manifesto. It
was written by a coalition of
Republicans and conservatively leaning
Democrats, the latter of which began as
Roosevelt's supporters, but had lost
faith that his programs were working.
More to the point, this group strongly
objected to the heavy-handed government
involvement required by the New Deal,
since they believed it was simply a
vehicle to introduce socialism and
communism. And although Roosevelt
largely ignored the conservative
criticism, this newly established
coalition in Congress was able to more
successfully oppose his policies now
that they had joined together. For
example, the conservatives on more than
one occasion took Roosevelt's New Deal
to the Supreme Court and won a few
cases, which effectively narrowed the
scope of what part of the New Deal was
constitutional and what part was
unconstitutional. Now, Roosevelt was
none too happy about this blocking
maneuver coming from the Supreme Court,
so he went ahead and proposed a judicial
reorganization bill, also known as the
court packing scheme. And basically,
this bill would allow the president to
appoint new Supreme Court justices for
every current justice that was older
than 70 and a half years. And by that
standard, Roosevelt could appoint six
additional judges to the Supreme Court
who would be sympathetic to the New Deal
and shut down the conservative
roadblock. But Congress went ahead and
shut that plan down because it was an
obvious and unconstitutional expansion
of executive power. But then on the
other side of the debate, liberals
criticized the New Deal because they
felt that Roosevelt didn't go far enough
using the government to solve the
problems of the depression. And this
criticism was leveled more from certain
portions of American society like black
Americans and women and Mexican
Americans. But maybe the best example of
this sides beef came from Huey Long, a
senator from Louisiana. He created the
Share Our Wealth Society, which was a
set of bills that introduced severe
taxation on the wealthy. And under this
plan, after the government collected
that money, it would redistribute that
wealth by guaranteeing every American a
$5,000 homestead and a guaranteed annual
income of $2,000. But it turned out that
the math didn't exactly math, and so the
tax revenue generated by that bill would
not have been enough to give every
American the amounts that Long had
promised. But even so, millions of
Americans joined Share Our Wealth clubs
and called for similar reforms expand
government intervention in their lives
even further than it already was. All
right, now let's finish this up by
considering the lasting effects of New
Deal legislation. But first, let me just
go ahead and tell you that on the whole,
the New Deal did not pull the United
States out of the Great Depression. What
ended it was the American mobilization
and entry into World War II, which
breathed enormous amounts of life into
the economy. However, even if the New
Deal didn't fully achieve its intended
goals, it made a deep and lasting change
on the United States going forward, two
of which you'll need to know. First of
all, the New Deal left a legacy of
reforms and regulatory agencies in the
American economic landscape. So, as I
mentioned earlier, the New Deal created
dozens of reforms and regulatory
agencies, some of which have remained in
place since the 1930s. And although
these entities were created in order to
reform irresponsible practices that led
to the Great Depression, apparently
Americans thought that the role such
policies and institutions played was a
step in the right direction for
long-term flourishing. For example, the
FDIC still insures bank deposits, the
Social Security Administration still
provides a financial safety net for
retirees, and the Security and Exchange
Commission continues to regulate the
stock market in order to prevent another
Black Tuesday disaster. But in the
second effect was a long-term
realignment of the two political
parties, which was fully apparent by the
election of 1936, which Roosevelt won in
an even bigger landslide than 1932. It
became clear that various ethnic groups
and working-class communities and black
Americans had consolidated their support
for the Democratic candidate. And that
switch was especially surprising for
black Americans. I mean, for the most
part, they had been deeply loyal to the
Republican Party who had fought for a
constitutional amendment recognizing
black men's right to vote. Not to
mention Republicans were the party that
ended slavery. But by the 1930s,
Republicans and Democrats were not
exactly the same parties they were in
the 19th century. And during the Great
Depression, black workers arguably
suffered more than anyone since they
were often the last hired and the first
fired. And since Republicans seemed to
be ignoring their plight, Roosevelt's
message of energetic and vigorous help
appealed to this demographic and they
voted Democrat as a block for the first
time in American history. And while
there were many factors that contributed
to such an outcome, I just want to tell
you about the advocacy work of Mary
McLeod Bethune. Now, she was a black
rights activist that worked in the
National Youth Administration, which was
a New Deal program that helped
unemployed young Americans. And Bethune
worked tirelessly to lobby the
organization to expand its provisions
for black youth. And for her efforts,
Roosevelt appointed her a national
advisor, and from that position, she
persuaded many black Americans that the
Roosevelt administration cared for the
improvement of black people and
therefore deserved their votes. Okay,
you can click here to watch my other
videos from Unit 7, or you can click
here to grab my video no-guys, which is
going to help you get all the concepts
of this course firmly crammed into your
brain vault. I'm glad you came around,
and I'll catch on the flip flop. I'm
Laroche.